<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Coastal Otago Willows and Weavers</title>
    <link href="https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/news" />
    <link type="application/atom+xml" rel="self" href="https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/news/feed.atom" />
    <updated>2024-06-13T20:24:02+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/news/feed.atom</id>
    <author>
        <name>Coastal Otago Willows and Weavers</name>
    </author>
                <entry>
    <id>https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/news/2024-05-29_end_of_season</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/news/2024-05-29_end_of_season" />
    <title>End of season and preparing for harvest</title>
    <published>2024-05-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2024-05-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Bronwyn Lowe</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">End of the weaving and growing season, and preparing for harvest....</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p>Can't believe it's almost harvest time again! There's been lots of action since last September, including running a few Beginners Workshops, weaving days for more intermediate members, a garden party at the willows to welcome the new year, a number of Committee meetings to continue our work towards incorporation, a visit from the American weaver Judy Zugish (listen to Judy discussing willows and weaving with us in <a href="https://accessmedia.nz/Player.aspx?eid=d00933cd-2dd7-4b5a-a70a-1884cfe8883b">this OI podcast</a>) and our fabulous Weaving Retreat in April.</p>

<p><x-img src="/assets/img/2024-05-mulching.jpg" caption='A thick mulch of sacks going down before harvest.' class="float-right w-1/3 mx-2 my-2"/></p>

<p>On the 25<sup>th</sup> of May we had our last workday at the willows before harvest. The day focussed on mulching the beds with sacks, and checking all our systems are go for the harvest to begin on 6<sup>th</sup> of July. Margaret had organised with Cerebos Greggs for us to pick up a load of coffee sacks the day before - thank you Margaret! And thank you to Cerebos Greggs for donating 4 pallets of sacks to the willow beds. Five cars and a trailer were packed to the gunnels. Gretchen had the grand idea of getting the sacks spread between the rows of willows straight away rather than waiting until after harvest - should give the sacks a chance to get wet and bed down a bit before harvest without having to peg or weight them. We're also hoping it will minimise the amount of mud between the rows if we have wet weather for harvest.</p>

<p><x-img src="/assets/img/2024-05-bird-mulch.jpg" caption="Willow beds looking beautiful in their autumn colours. Spot the Pīwakawaka photo bombing Jill's head!" class="float-right w-1/3 mx-2 my-2"/></p>

<p>Meanwhile the willows having been growing well, despite a very dry autumn. We're thinking that some of the varieties haven't grown as tall this year due the dry weather. Its going to be interesting to see whether there's any effect on the weaving properties of this year's crop. Luckily there was no sign of aphids until quite late in the growing season, and the infestation on the willows was relatively light and short-lived. Too dry for them too? Who knows. The willows are looking very healthy overall. The beds are now almost three years old, and the number and size of rods produced by each stool will be approaching what we can expect from mature beds. It promises to be a very good harvest this year!</p>

<p>Put the harvest dates in your calendar and come along. Join us on the weekends of the 6<sup>th</sup> - 7<sup>th</sup> and 13<sup>th</sup> - 14<sup>th</sup> of July 2024, 10am to 4pm each day. More information will be posted closer to harvest time.</p>
    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/news/2023-09-30_new_name</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/news/2023-09-30_new_name" />
    <title>We have changed our name!</title>
    <published>2023-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2023-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Bronwyn Lowe</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">We are now Coastal Otago Willows and Weavers....</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p>Our new name is Coastal Otago Willows and Weavers!</p>

<p>We have been discussing for some time whether to change our name, now that our willow beds are no longer located on the Taieri Plain and we’re enjoying an ever increasing range of weaving activities. At our AGM on 25<sup>th</sup> September 2023, a list of potential names and a voting method was approved. The list of names was sent to everyone on our gmail list, and voting closed 30<sup>th</sup> September. We think the new name is good, it tells the story of where we are and what we do.</p>
    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/news/2023-07-23_annual_harvest</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/news/2023-07-23_annual_harvest" />
    <title>Annual Harvest, Seacliff</title>
    <published>2023-07-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2023-07-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Bronwyn Lowe</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">A good harvest for our second year at the Seacliff willow beds....</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p>We got the annual willow harvest done over three weekends in July, with some truly lovely willow harvested even though the beds are only two years old. The first day of harvest on 8th of July focussed on improving our harvest methods and systems. With so many different varieties, it’s important to make sure they don’t get mixed up as they get cut, sorted, sized and tied into bundles. A key improvement was adding a preliminary sorting step where branched, broken, bent or damaged willow rods were put into a separate 'seconds' pile. Seconds were further separated into potentially useful rods, for example for making frames, using as base sticks, or making garden structures. The rest was cut up for kindling. Meanwhile, the good willow was sorted into size classes for bundling.</p>

<p><x-img src="/assets/img/sorting onto tarps.jpg" caption='Sorting onto tarps' class="float-right w-1/3 mx-2 my-2"/></p>

<p>It gets quite muddy in the sorting areas with all the foot traffic, so we sort the willow onto tarps. A great innovation this year was marking lines on the tarps for the various height classes, much easier to sort the willow into consistent size classes! Although there was some debate whether to use traditional 'foot' sizes, or to go metric – we settled on foot sizes for ease of writing the numbers on all the labels.</p>

<p><x-img src="/assets/img/bundling and labelling.jpg" caption='Bundling and labelling' class="float-right w-1/3 mx-2 my-2"/></p>

<p>This year we’re trying out using recycled bicycle tubes for tying the willow bundles, an idea Maia picked up from the team at <a href="https://www.rekindle.org.nz/">Rekindle</a> in Christchurch. A few bicycle shops around Dunedin were happy to give us bags of discarded bicycle tubes. We cut the tubes into smaller strips for tying. We certainly need a LOT of ties.</p>

<p><x-img src="/assets/img/Cutting bike tubes 2023.jpg" caption='Cutting bike tubes' class="float-right w-1/3 mx-2 my-2"/></p>

<p>Once again, a big thankyou to our neighbour Amanda for making a large shed available for storing the harvested willow bundles. The shed is just down the road, so we pile all the bundled willow into Belinda’s ute at the end of each harvest day and drive it down there.</p>

<p><x-img src="/assets/img/Green Dicks bundles.jpg" caption='Green Dicks bundles' class="float-right w-1/3 mx-2 my-2"/></p>

<p>We drafted up a "Harvest Protocol" while we were going, documenting all the key steps and equipment. This will be very useful to refer to when we’re setting up for harvest next year and teaching people the various tasks it takes to bring in a good harvest. There’s a lot of willow to harvest now at the Seacliff beds, and it’s great to have a system sorted that makes the whole process efficient, improves the skills of our harvesters and hopefully keeps harvest a fun event!</p>

<p><x-img src="/assets/img/last stool cut.jpg" caption='Last stool cut' class="float-right w-1/3 mx-2 my-2"/></p>

<p>And finally, so good to have the Tool Shed on site - thankyou Waikouaiti Coast Community Board for funding this very useful shed. Very quick to pack up and put away all the harvest gear at the end of each day– tarps, sorting tables, bags of ties, tools, lunch gear, washing up gear etc etc. Between the Tool Shed and our documented Harvest Protocol, harvest next year should go like a dream!</p>

<p>Now we’re all looking forward to a whole year of weaving projects – we’re currently drafting up a calendar of events and will be publishing it on this website soon, so keep an eye out!</p>
    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/news/2023-07-16_tool_shed_install</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/news/2023-07-16_tool_shed_install" />
    <title>Tool shed completed just in time for harvest</title>
    <published>2023-07-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2023-07-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Bronwyn Lowe</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">Thank you to the Waikouaiti Coast Community Board and Bunnings for supporting our group....</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p>We turned the first sod on the tool shed site on 22<sup>nd</sup> of June, digging holes and ramming in the piles for the shed foundation. We took delivery of the Duratuf Tool Shed kit from Bunnings on 27<sup>th</sup> of June. <strong>Thank you to Bunnings for supporting our project by donating the heavy-duty workbench, security alarm and combination lock for the shed.</strong> Construction of the shed progressed steadily, aiming for completion in time for our annual harvest.</p>

<p><x-img src="/assets/img/preparing foundations.jpg" caption='Preparing the shed foundation' class="float-right w-1/3 mx-2 my-2"/></p>

<p>We got the floor down the day before the start of harvest on the 8<sup>th</sup> of July, however we didn’t get the doors on due to a glitch with their size. Nonetheless it was great to have dry storage on site for all our harvest equipment that first wet weekend! The doors were fixed and in place by the second weekend of harvest, and we rapidly filled the now completed shed with even more harvesting paraphernalia.</p>

<p><x-img src="/assets/img/assembling walls.jpg" caption='Assembling the walls' class="float-right w-1/3 mx-2 my-2"/></p>

<p><x-img src="/assets/img/securing roof.jpg" caption='Securing the roof and preparing to lay the timber floor' class="float-right w-1/3 mx-2 my-2"/></p>

<p>Assembling the heavy-duty workbench quickly became a priority, and by the end of pack-up on Sunday 16<sup>th</sup> July we had a very tidy shed, with the beginnings of a good storage system. It's fantastic to have this shed at the willow beds – <strong>a huge thankyou to the Waikouaiti Coast Community Board for supporting our group and providing the majority of the funding for the shed purchase!</strong></p>

<p><x-img src="/assets/img/nearly completed for harvest.jpg" caption='The almost completed shed in use for the first day of willow harvest 2023' class="float-right w-1/3 mx-2 my-2"/></p>

<p><x-img src="/assets/img/organising shed storage.jpg" caption='Organising storage inside the shed' class="float-right w-1/3 mx-2 my-2"/></p>
    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/news/2023-05-14_tool_shed</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/news/2023-05-14_tool_shed" />
    <title>Full steam ahead to purchase a Tool Shed!</title>
    <published>2023-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2023-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Bronwyn Lowe</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">Thank you to the Waikouaiti Coast Community Board for funding to purchase a Tool Shed....</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p>In February we applied to the Waikouaiti Coast Community Board for funding to purchase a Tool Shed. Bron and Julie attended the Board meeting to speak to our application. The Board were interested in what our group does, and very generously decided to fund us with $2,000 towards purchasing a Duratuf kit set tool shed! Thank you so much to the Waikouaiti Coast Community Board, it's going to make a huge difference to have a shed on site for storing our tools, mulching resources, harvest equipment etc. Last week we finally completed the process of getting a bank account set up to receive the funding. This week we’re getting on with ordering the shed, aiming for a shed raising working bee in mid-June. It’s going to be so good to have the Tool Shed there in time for harvest this year!</p>
    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/news/2023-05-13_weeding_mulching_aphids</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/news/2023-05-13_weeding_mulching_aphids" />
    <title>Weeding, Mulching and Aphid Day</title>
    <published>2023-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2023-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Bronwyn Lowe</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">We added in an extra work day in the willow beds this month to target the willow aphids....</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p><x-img src="/assets/img/IMG_20230513_133851654.jpg" caption='' class="float-right w-1/3 mx-2 my-2"/></p>

<p>We added in an extra work day in the willow beds this month to target the willow aphids. We’ve had quite a big infestation this year, heaviest on the taller varieties at the southern end of the bed, but spreading into the Green Dicks and Nana too. Gretchen and Maia did a staunch job of spraying with Neem oil, while the rest of us worked at the other end of the main bed, weeding and mulching the Nana and Lancashire Dicks. The sacks from Cerebos Gregg are breaking down and forming a very good mulch material. We’re continuing with laying cardboard, then sacks on top to supress the grass. A couple of weeks ago the hedge on the east side was trimmed and chipped, giving us a big pile of chippings to spread as mulch too. The shorter willow varieties, particularly Nana and Lancashire Dicks, were getting very choked and smothered by the tall grasses this year. Its very satisfying to get them looking all happy and beautiful again with the lovely mulch.</p>

<p><x-img src="/assets/img/IMG_20230513_151326365.jpg" caption='Maia and her greenwood stool.' class="float-right w-1/3 mx-2 my-2"/></p>

<p>Maia also brought along the gorgeous greenwood stool she’s made to show us. Beautiful work Maia!</p>
    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/news/2023-02-08_incorporated_society</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/news/2023-02-08_incorporated_society" />
    <title>We are becoming an Incorporated Society!</title>
    <published>2023-02-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2023-02-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Bronwyn Lowe</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">On Wednesday the 8th of February 2023 we held a meeting in the Dunningham Suite, Dunedin Public Library, for members to discuss and agree on our process for becoming an Incorporated Society....</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p>It’s been a busy summer of not only getting on with mulching and weeding the willow beds, but also lots of fruitful discussion about formalising our group. This is important so that we can get on with raising funds for building a small Tool Shed for our work tools and mulch materials, and then... a larger shed for processing and storing our annual willow harvest! After much debate, discussion with Anna Parker of Matawai Associates, finding out about how other community groups operate and advice from Maia’s solicitor, we decided that becoming an Incorporated Society is the best choice.</p>

<p>On Wednesday the 8th of February 2023 we held a meeting in the Dunningham Suite, Dunedin Public Library, for members to discuss and agree on our process for becoming an Incorporated Society. Twenty members attended the meeting, with apologies from a number of people who were unable to attend. There was unanimous support to go ahead with incorporating, with sub groups set up to get on with preparing the application for incorporation. So now it’s full steam ahead, there’s a lot of mahi to get done, but we hope to be incorporated by April sometime!</p>
    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/news/2023-01-03_owaka</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/news/2023-01-03_owaka" />
    <title>Field Trip to Owaka willows</title>
    <published>2023-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2023-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Jill Thomson</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">The invitation from Monica and Carla to visit their garden and willow bed in Owaka was taken up by 5 of us on a glorious day in early January....</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p>The invitation from Monica and Carla to visit their garden and willow bed in Owaka was taken up by 5 of us on a glorious day in early January. Any excuse to get to the Catlins is tempting and what we saw and heard about was inspiring, if not a little daunting. We marvelled at the vege plot, the nursery, the tunnel house, the fruit and nut trees...not to mention the beginnings of a new willow bed. </p>

<p>As if the work here wasn't enough, after a  picnic lunch in the garden  we drove the few minutes to the Owaka township. An old church hall has been purchased and already used for community market days and selling fresh produce. As we were shown around our eyes were lighting up at the potential for the use of this space for willow basket workshops.
Buzzing with ideas we needed to calm ourselves with an amble through the cool forest cover of the Pounawea bush walk. That moment when you come out of the forest and onto the inlet beach is stunning.</p>

<p>Thanks so much to Carla, Monica and whanau for your time and generosity. We headed back to Dunedin energised and excited at the prospect of  pooling the considerable knowledge within this group and making baskets in Owaka together.</p>
    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/news/2022-12-17_mulch_and_toast</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/news/2022-12-17_mulch_and_toast" />
    <title>Mulch and Toast!</title>
    <published>2022-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2022-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Bronwyn Lowe</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">Join the end-of-year celebration and last working bee at the willow beds for 2022. Saturday 17th of December 1 – 4 pm....</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p>Join the end-of-year celebration and last working bee at the willow beds for 2022. Saturday 17th of December 1 – 4 pm. BYO drinks, a plate to share and baskets for show and tell (and a camp chair or picnic rug).</p>

<p>We’re planning about an hour of work to lift the last of the remaining weedmat and deep mulch that area in preparation for winter planting. Bring gloves and a yard shark or similar tool for cutting long grass. After we’re done mulching it’s put down your tools and put your feet up for our end-of-year afternoon tea party! A good chance to discuss ideas and dates for things we’d like to do in 2023 too.</p>
    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/news/2022-11-26_weeding_days</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/news/2022-11-26_weeding_days" />
    <title>November Weeding Days</title>
    <published>2022-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2022-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Bronwyn Lowe</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">We decided to fit in an extra day of weeding as well as the usual last Saturday of the month to keep ahead of the weeds and get as much mulching done as possible....</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p>All the warm then wet weather of October and November meant rapid growth of weeds and willows. We decided to fit in an extra day of weeding as well as the usual last Saturday of the month to keep ahead of the weeds and get as much mulching done as possible. A great turnout both days, thankyou everyone! The 12th was a rather hot humid afternoon, and we had to retreat to the shade for afternoon tea!</p>

<p><x-img src="/assets/img/IMG_20221111_164148890_HDR.jpg" caption='' class="float-right w-1/3 mx-2 my-2"/></p>

<p>Maia and Bron had picked up a trailer load of sawdust, and we mixed the sawdust with grass clippings to make a satisfyingly deep mulch over the cardboard+sack mulch layer among the willows.</p>

<p><x-img src="/assets/img/IMG_20221112_155355744.jpg" caption='' class="float-right w-1/3 mx-2 my-2"/></p>

<p>The willows are looking great after all this work, and it’s obvious we are going to be rewarded with a very good harvest, even though the willows are only in their second year.</p>
    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/news/2022-11-06_spring_beginners_workshops</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/news/2022-11-06_spring_beginners_workshops" />
    <title>Spring Beginners Workshops</title>
    <published>2022-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2022-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Bronwyn Lowe</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">We ran two beginners workshops this spring, using rods stored from the last few harvests from the Taieri willow beds....</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p>We ran two beginners workshops this spring, using rods stored from the last few harvests from the Taieri willow beds. We always begin our workshops with a visit to the willow beds and a discussion of what’s involved in growing, harvesting and preparing willow for weaving.</p>

<p><x-img src="/assets/img/IMG_20221125_135901142_HDR.jpg" caption='Making bodkins for our group.' class="float-right w-1/3 mx-2 my-2"/></p>

<p>My partner is a skilled metal worker, and we’re incredibly lucky that he recently offered to make a set of bodkins for our group to use at workshops and weaving get togethers. These beautiful bodkins got their first proper workout at the workshops.</p>

<p>Once again the enthusiastic participants worked hard and produced incredibly beautiful baskets!</p>

<p><x-img src="/assets/img/IMG_20221106_152352993.jpg" caption='' class="float-right w-1/3 mx-2 my-2"/></p>

<p><x-img src="/assets/img/IMG_20221008_163036758.jpg" caption='' class="float-right w-1/3 mx-2 my-2"/></p>

<p><x-img src="/assets/img/IMG_20221009_115807170_HDR.jpg" caption='' class="float-right w-1/3 mx-2 my-2"/></p>

<p><x-img src="/assets/img/IMG_20221009_164537146.jpg" caption='' class="float-right w-1/3 mx-2 my-2"/></p>

<p><x-img src="/assets/img/IMG_20221106_154934864.jpg" caption='' class="float-right w-1/3 mx-2 my-2"/></p>
    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/news/2022-10-29_weeding_and_weaving</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/news/2022-10-29_weeding_and_weaving" />
    <title>Combined weaving and weeding day</title>
    <published>2022-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2022-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Bronwyn Lowe</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">The October willow weaving and weeding days were combined into one full Saturday....</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p>The October willow weaving and weeding days were combined into one full Saturday. In the morning people started on their frame baskets. The rods bent onto the formas back in August were used to make the frame hoops. A variety of materials including harakeke strips and soaked cane were used to bind the hoops and weave the Gods Eyes.</p>

<p><x-img src="/assets/img/IMG_20211122_174911449.jpg" caption='' class="float-right w-1/3 mx-2 my-2"/></p>

<p>One of the advantages of frame baskets is that the infill weaving of the body of the basket doesn’t have to be completed in one go. Weavers can soak up small batches of willow or use alternative materials to keep working on completing the baskets over time.</p>

<p><x-img src="/assets/img/IMG_20221029_164728406.jpg" caption='' class="float-right w-1/3 mx-2 my-2"/></p>

<p>After lunch we headed up to the willow beds for a few hours. Great to see the willow growing so strongly already! However the weeds are also growing apace, and it’s a critical time of year to keep the weeds from smothering the young willow growth, particularly the smaller varieties like Salix purpurea ‘Nana’. In another couple of months the willow will have grown taller and better able to battle the weeds by shading them out.</p>

<p><x-img src="/assets/img/IMG_20221029_164803135.jpg" caption='' class="float-right w-1/3 mx-2 my-2"/></p>

<p>We focused on weeding out and mulching the smaller varieties of willow, laying sacks between the rows then covering the sacks with cut grass and weeds to weigh the sacks down. We didn’t want a repeat of what happened last year when the sacks were lifted and blown about by that nasty nor-wester!</p>

<p><x-img src="/assets/img/IMG_20221029_164711742.jpg" caption='' class="float-right w-1/3 mx-2 my-2"/></p>

<p>We also started on lifting the weedmat section that had become overgrown with grass, a difficult and horrible job! This section was set aside for future plantings when we first established the beds in September 2021. We’re planning to use this space to plant new varieties, or increase the number of stools of varieties that we already have and particularly like for weaving.</p>
    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/news/2022-09-18_weaving_get_together</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/news/2022-09-18_weaving_get_together" />
    <title>September Weaving Get-Together</title>
    <published>2022-09-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2022-09-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Bronwyn Lowe</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">Making bases at our September weaving get-together...</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p>The September get-together was focused on making bases. Julie brought along a huge bundle of semi-dried Leicestershire Dicks, Maia had a semi-dried bundle of a lovely green local unknown variety and Maia had also soaked up some Nana and Green Dicks. Lots of choice for weaving with!  Some people kept honing their skills on round bases, whilst Julie, Bron and Maia had a go at English oval bases using the hand and foot method. Thanks for bringing the instructional video along Julie, that was great fun!</p>

<p><x-img src="/assets/img/IMG_20220918_142647608.jpg" caption='' class="float-right w-1/3 mx-2 my-2"/></p>

<p>We also unloaded a great pile of coffee sacks at the willow beds, in preparation for mulching the beds again. Thanks Margaret for once again organising for us to pick up sacks from Cerebos-Greggs, and big thanks to Cerebos-Greggs for donating three pallets of sacks to our group. We had four vehicles packed to the gunnels with sacks!</p>

<!-- <x-img src="/assets/img/IMG_1377.jpg" caption='' class="float-right w-1/3 mx-2 my-2"/> -->
    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/news/2022-08-21_weaving_get_together</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/news/2022-08-21_weaving_get_together" />
    <title>August Weaving Get-Together</title>
    <published>2022-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2022-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Bronwyn Lowe</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">Using formas at our August weaving get-together...</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p>At the August get-together we used formas to bend rods into rounds and ovals for frame baskets and handles. The formas we used are slabs of wood drilled with a grid of holes to take large removable wooden pegs. Rods of semi-dried willow and hazel were bent and held in place by pegs spaced appropriately on the formas. The pegs are tall enough to bend a number of rods around each shape. The rods now stay on the formas to dry for a couple of months, after which we will have a great stash of bent rods for future basket making!</p>

<p><x-img src="/assets/img/IMG_1371.jpg" caption='' class="float-right w-1/3 mx-2 my-2"/></p>

<!-- <x-img src="/assets/img/IMG_1377.jpg" caption='' class="float-right w-1/3 mx-2 my-2"/> -->
    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/news/2022-07-15_annual_harvest</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/news/2022-07-15_annual_harvest" />
    <title>Annual Harvest, Seacliff</title>
    <published>2022-07-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2022-07-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Bronwyn Lowe</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">We were really fortunate and had a perfect weather window for the inaugural Seacliff harvest....</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p>We were really fortunate and had a perfect weather window for the inaugural Seacliff harvest. Lots of helpers, lovely sunshine and no wind added great spirit to the day. Fantastic team-work saw us harvest, sort, bundle and move to storage the majority of the willow in a single day. Big thanks to Amanda for providing us with a storage room just a short distance from the willow beds, to Margaret for making two big pots of soup for our lunch, and to everyone who came along and worked hard all day. It was very rewarding to harvest a fairly decent amount of usable willow from this first year of growth. All the care and hard work establishing the willow beds last spring was well worth it!</p>

<div class="clear-both float-right w-1/3 mx-2 my-2" >
    <img src="https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/assets/img/IMG_20220710_133907061.jpg" class="rounded-md" alt="Harvested rods of one-year old Salix purpurea &quot;Nana&quot;, all very short with dense branching."/>
            <p class="text-xs text-slate-500 text-center">Harvested rods of one-year old Salix purpurea &quot;Nana&quot;, all very short with dense branching.</p>
    </div>

<div class="clear-both float-right w-1/3 mx-2 my-2" >
    <img src="https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/assets/img/IMG_20220710_113743844.jpg" class="rounded-md" alt="Making short work of the Salix purpurea &quot;Green Dicks&quot; section of the willow bed. The taller growing cultivar on the left is Salix triandra &quot;Black Maul&quot;."/>
            <p class="text-xs text-slate-500 text-center">Making short work of the Salix purpurea &quot;Green Dicks&quot; section of the willow bed. The taller growing cultivar on the left is Salix triandra &quot;Black Maul&quot;.</p>
    </div>

<p>The willow that was unsuitable for basketmaking due to branching of the rods and small size has been cut into kindling size pieces, and is bagged up. <a href="/contact">Get in touch with us</a> if you would like some kindling (you will need to store it for a while, needs to dry out before it will burn).</p>

<div class="clear-both float-right w-1/3 mx-2 my-2" >
    <img src="https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/assets/img/IMG_20220710_134122401.jpg" class="rounded-md" alt="Harvesting Salix purpurea &quot;Lancashire Dicks&quot;, Salix eriocephala &quot;Americana&quot; and Salix purpurea &quot;Leistershire Dicks&quot;."/>
            <p class="text-xs text-slate-500 text-center">Harvesting Salix purpurea &quot;Lancashire Dicks&quot;, Salix eriocephala &quot;Americana&quot; and Salix purpurea &quot;Leistershire Dicks&quot;.</p>
    </div>

<div class="clear-both float-right w-1/3 mx-2 my-2" >
    <img src="https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/assets/img/IMG_20220710_113835465.jpg" class="rounded-md" alt="Sorting, grading and bundling Salix purpurea &quot;Green Dicks&quot;"/>
            <p class="text-xs text-slate-500 text-center">Sorting, grading and bundling Salix purpurea &quot;Green Dicks&quot;</p>
    </div>

<p>A lot of the willow harvested this year had multiple branching on the rods. Unfortunately, the branched material is not very good for basketmaking. The rods tend to break at the branch point while weaving, and the branches leave a stub on the rod that is hard on the hands and eye. We were able to rescue some material but cutting off and keeping longer side branches that were not branched themselves. Branching is fairly typical in the first year of growth of a new willow bed, as there is very little competition for light between the young stools. New growth tends to branch and sprawl sideways to fill space rather than racing against neighbouring stools to reach up to the sky. Individual rods also tend to be shorter and thinner than is typical for mature stools. We’re expecting the willows to be producing rods typical of mature stools by their third year.</p>

<div class="clear-both float-right w-1/3 mx-2 my-2" >
    <img src="https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/assets/img/IMG_20220710_130848558_HDR.jpg" class="rounded-md" alt="A well earned break for lunch. Hot soup and buns much appreciated by all!"/>
            <p class="text-xs text-slate-500 text-center">A well earned break for lunch. Hot soup and buns much appreciated by all!</p>
    </div>

<p>The natural growth habit of willows varies from low growing shrubs to tall trees, depending on the species and variety. When coppiced in a willow bed, this growth habit controls the size of the rods produced. Our smallest variety is <em>Salix purpurea</em> "Nana", our largest is <em>Salix viminalis</em> "Mr Green", which can produce rods over 3 metres tall. <em>Salix purpurea</em> "Green Dicks" is a reliable basket making cultivar, producing rods good for small to medium sized baskets. We have planted multiple rows of this variety, to provide a good bulk of material every year for our members, as well as material for <a href="https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/workshops">our workshops</a>.</p>

<p><em>Salix purpurea</em> "Lancashire Dicks", <em>Salix eriocephala</em> "Americana" and <em>Salix purpurea</em> "Leicestershire Dicks" all grow naturally as shrubs rather than trees. In this first year they have all tended to sprawl out sideways, filling space horizontally rather than growing up vertically. We expect taller, vertical rods on these stools as they mature over the next couple of years and produce a greater number of rods per stool. More rods per stool creates greater competition for light, and the rods grow straight and tall as they reach for the sun.</p>

<p>After cutting, the rods from each variety were carried to separate sorting areas. This year we sorted into branched and un-branched rods first. The branched rods are usually not good for weaving with, and were cut into short lengths for kindling and bagged. Un-branched rods were graded according to rod length and tied into bundles. Sorting drums make it easier to stand the rods on end and select out groups of rods of similar length (see Sorting for photos of this process)</p>

<p>We are working on raising funds to build a work and storage shed in the area we currently use for our picnics. We plan to build a shed that will give us a dry work space, somewhere to have lunch and cuppas out of the weather, and storage for the harvested willow.</p>
    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/news/2022-06-25_weeding_before_harvest</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/news/2022-06-25_weeding_before_harvest" />
    <title>Last Weeding Day Before Harvest</title>
    <published>2022-06-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2022-06-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Bronwyn Lowe</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">A great turn out of helpers to do the last tidy of the willow beds before harvest....</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p>A great turn out of helpers to do the last tidy of the willow beds before harvest. All the willows have dropped their leaves now, a good indicator that we can go ahead with harvest. Maia and Nicky have done a great job cutting the grass around the outside of the beds, so that we have easy access and good sorting areas for harvest day. The rest of us pulled weeds from around the stools, and started laying a new mulch of sacks between the rows. A big thankyou to Cerebos Greggs for donating bundles of coffee sacks to our group, and to Margaret for organising and picking up the sacks. The sacks are a fantastic weed-supressing mulch.</p>

<p><x-img src="/assets/img/IMG_20220625_144020377.jpg" caption='' class="float-right w-1/3 mx-2 my-2"/></p>
    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/news/2022-02-26_february_weeding_day</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/news/2022-02-26_february_weeding_day" />
    <title>February Weeding Day</title>
    <published>2022-02-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2022-02-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Bronwyn Lowe</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">A lovely warm day for cutting grass and pulling out weeds....</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p>A lovely warm day for cutting grass and pulling out weeds. The willows are really growing fast, putting on lots of height and leaf. The differences between the varieties are much more obvious now with the different heights, leaf colour and leaf shapes. Very pleasing to see our cardboard+sacks mulch still working well to supress the weeds around the young stools.</p>
    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/news/2021-12-11_weeding_the_willow_beds</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/news/2021-12-11_weeding_the_willow_beds" />
    <title>Weeding the Willow Beds</title>
    <published>2021-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2021-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Bronwyn Lowe</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">We had a great afternoon today weeding the new willow beds....</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p>Great afternoon today weeding the new willow beds. Very encouraging to see great growth on the cuttings and very few weeds coming through our cardboard + coffee sack mulch. A few areas had couch sneaking through where the cardboard layer had gaps, so we did some patching by unpinning and lifting sacks and tucking fresh cardboard underneath. Only 2 dead cuttings out of the 1200+ we planted in September! Looking forward to seeing even more good growth when we have our next weeding day, scheduled for January 29th 2022. See you there!</p>

<p><x-img src="/assets/img/IMG_20211211_135711123.jpg" caption='' class="float-right w-1/3 mx-2 my-2"/></p>
    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/news/2021-10-31_new_willow_beds</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://www.taieriwillow.org.nz/news/2021-10-31_new_willow_beds" />
    <title>New Willow Beds</title>
    <published>2021-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2021-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Bronwyn Lowe</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">Finished the new willow beds....</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p>Celebration of completing the planting of the new willow beds at Seacliff 31st October 2021</p>
    ]]></content>
</entry>
    </feed>
